Krueger mss., 1988-1993 LMC 2262 (VAD8303) (VAD8303)
Lilly Library
Krueger mss.
1988-1993
Lilly Library
Krueger, Gertraude.
LMC 2262 (VAD8303) (VAD8303)
5 Boxes 5 standard
The Krueger mss., 1988-1993, consist of translations from English into German of literary works by British authors Julian Barnes and William Boyd. The translator is Gertraude Krueger of Berlin and the translations were published by Haffmans Verlag in Zurich in the case of Barnes and by Rowohlt Verlag in Hamburg for Boyd.
Access Restrictions
This collection is open for research.
Biographical Note
Gertraude Krueger, of Berlin, translated works by British authors Julian Barnes and William Boyd and works by American author Valerie Wilson Wesley from English into German.
Scope and Content Note
The Krueger mss., 1988-1993, consist of translations from English into German of literary works by British authors Julian Barnes and William Boyd. The translator is Gertraude Krueger of Berlin and the translations were published by Haffmans Verlag in Zurich in the case of Barnes and by Rowohlt Verlag in Hamburg for Boyd.
Additions to the Krueger mss., 1995-1996, are first draft translations into German of two books by American author Valerie Wilson Wesley: When Death Comes Stealing (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1994) and Devil's Gonna Get Him (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, 1995). The former was published as Ein Engel über deinem Grab (Zurich: Diogenes Verlag, 1996); the latter as In Teufels Küche (Zurich: Diogenes Verlag, 1998). Both manuscripts are accompanied by photocopies of correspondence from Krueger to her editor at Diogenes Verlag as well as notes and queries regarding appropriate translations of words and phrases.
Acquisition Information
Acquired: 2001, 2002
English literature --Translations into German.; American literature --Translations into German.; Translators.; Translators --Correspondence.; Publishers and publishing --Germany --Correspondence.; Publishers and publishing --Switzerland --Correspondence.; Krueger, Gertraude.; Barnes, Julian --Translations into German.; Boyd, William, 1952- --Translations into German.; Wesley, Valerie Wilson --Translations into German.
- Barnes, Julian.Metroland. (London: Jonathan Cape, )., 1980
  - First complete draft, in German., (3 folders)
  - Accompanying materials, (1 folder)
    Scope and Contents
    Photocopies of queries to Barnes, with his answers, 7p.
    Photocopies of correspondence between Krueger and her editor at Haffmans Verlag about the translation, 4p.
    Preparatory notes, 13p.
    Two earlier drafts of pages 73-78, 15p.
    Other notes and queries, 9p.
- Barnes, Julian.Staring at the Sun. (London: Jonathan Cape, )., 1986
  - First complete draft, in German., (3 folders)
  - Accompanying materials, (1 folder)
    Photocopies of Krueger's queries to Barnes, with his answers, Nov. 1990-Mar. 1991 [6]p.
    Holograph preparatory notes, mostly re: terminology [25]p.
    Acknowledgements, 1p.
- Boyd, William.Brazzaville Beach. (London: Sinclair-Stevenson, )., 1990
  - First draft translation into German with numerous revisions and changes in pencil and some in ink., (3 folders)
  - Accompanying materials, (1 folder)
    "Fragen an William Boyd zu Brazzaville Beach," 1p.
    Holograph preparatory notes, 11p.
    Clippings from German newspapers, etc. with certain words or phrases marked.
- Wesley, Valerie Wilson.When Death Comes Stealing (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, )., 1994
  - First draft translation in German with numerous revisions and changes in pencil. Dated on last page., 20-2-96; (2 folders)
  - Accompanying materials, (1 folder)
    Copies of correspondence
    Notes and queries to German colleagues and American friends
    Notes on conversation with publisher's reader
    Notes on brand names
    Newspaper article from Der Tagesspiegel, 12 November 1995, on marijuana.
- Wesley, Valerie Wilson.Devil's Gonna Get Him (New York: G.P. Putnam's Sons, )., 1995
  - First draft translation in German with frequent revisions and changes in pencil., (2 folders)
  - Accompanying materials, (1 folder)
    Copies of correspondence, notes and queries of German and American colleagues
    Questions and suggestions by Judge Hartmut Fischer
    Questions and suggestions by physician Caroline Einkämpl.